Sorosis Records, 1856-1972
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Sorosis records
1856-1972
Sorosis
356
31 boxes (12.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Women's club. The Sorosis records include by-laws, constitutions, minutes, membership lists, yearbooks, programs, reports, histories, speeches, writings, clippings, subject files, memorabilia, publications, printed material, and scrapbooks. The Records document the club's advocacy of temperance, prison reform, and peace, as well as their programs in art, drama, education, and music. Included are bound copies of Executive Committee minutes (1884-1907, 1937-1965); and committee reports (1886-1947). There are also biographical materials, writings, and photographs of first president Jane C. Croly (1829-1901); material relating to the Women's Congress in New York City (1873-1877); and the Association for the Advancement of Women (established by Sorosis in 1873).
Sorosis is an organization of professional and literary women founded in New York City in 1868. Columnist "Jennie June" (Jane C. Croly) and other women journalists were denied tickets to a New York Press Club event honoring Charles Dickens. The presenters claimed that the presence of the women would make the occasion "promiscuous." Offended, the female journalists founded their own press club, naming it Sorosis after a botanical term referring to plants with a grouping of flowers that bore fruit. The term was meant to symbolize women's determination to transform supposedly delicate and feeble ladies into important members of public society. Jane Croly organized a group of her friends, many of whom were writers, into the club to "promote agreeable and useful relations among women," particularly those who had found "expression in outward life and work." The club's mission was to "establish a freemasonry among women of similar pursuits....[to afford] an opportunity for discussion...the results of which promise to exert an important influence on the future of women and the welfare of society." Historian Karen J. Blair states that the members tended to be "career women who had become keenly aware of sexism in their struggle for professional success."1
New York's Sorosis and Boston's New England Woman's Club (both founded in 1868) inspired the formation of women's clubs across the country. Croly called a national convention of women's clubs in 1869 that eventually led to the formation of the Association for the Advancement of Women (1873) and the General Federation of Women's Clubs (1890).
From the very beginning members of Sorosis have been prominent participants in varied professions and political reform movements such as abolitionism, suffrage, prison reform, temperance and peace. Although the discussion of suffrage was forbidden in an effort to create a safe feeling of unity among the members, many Sorosis members were staunchly in favor of, and involved in, the suffrage movement.
Sorosis expanded into local chapters beyond New York City in the early twentieth century and the various chapters went on to organize war relief efforts during both World Wars. Peace time activities included philanthropy (such as support for funding the MacDowell Colony), scholarship funds, and social reforms (such as literary training for immigrant women). In later years, Sorosis focused its activities on local projects, raising money for the aid of other women's clubs, funding scholarships for women, and aiding local rescue missions. Presidents of the club have included Alice Cary, Jennie C. Croly, Charlotte B. Wilbour, M. Louise Thomas, Ella Dietz Clymer and Jennie de la M. Lozier. Sorosis continues to thrive in New York City with an active charitable agenda.
1: Karen J. Blair, The Clubwoman as Feminist: True Womanhood Redefined, 1868-1914 (Homes and Meier Publishers, New York: 1980): 21.
The Sorosis records include by-laws, constitutions, minutes, membership lists, yearbooks, programs, reports, histories, speeches, writings, clippings, subject files, memorabilia, publications, printed material, and scrapbooks.
The Records document the club's advocacy of temperance, prison reform, and peace, as well as their programs in art, drama, education, and music. Included are bound copies of Executive Committee minutes (1884-1907, 1937-1965); and committee reports (1886-1947). There are also biographical materials, writings, and photographs of first president Jane C. Croly (1829-1901); material relating to the Women's Congress in New York City (1873-1877); and the Association for the Advancement of Women (established by Sorosis in 1873).
This collection is organized into eight series:
I. MEETINGS, 1868-1965
II. ADMINISTRATION AND ORGANIZATION, 1870-1985
III. HISTORY, 1871-1973, n.d.
IV. OFFICERS, 1894-1950
V. MEMBERS, 1868-1975, n.d.
VI. PUBLICATIONS, 1869-1966
VII. RELATED ORGANIZATIONS, 1885-1937
VIII. MEMORABILIA, 1880-1968
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
The following records are also available on microfiche in History of Women located in the William Allen Neilson Library: Minutes, 1868-1937; Executive Committee Minutes, 1884-1907; Report of the 21st Anniversary of Sorosis celebrated by a Convention of Clubs held in New York City, March 1889; Selections from the Writings of the Presidents of Sorosis, A Souvenir of the Breakfast at Sherry's, March 30, 1893.
Periodic additions to this collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
The bulk of the records were donated in 1968 by the then President of Sorosis Dorothy Valentine Smith. In 1980 and 1987 Helen-Louise C. Fullman donated additional materials including scrapbooks, published material, and anniversary programs.
Croly, J. C. (Jane Cunningham), 1829-1901; Cary, Alice, 1820-1871; Cary, Phoebe, 1824-1871; Hanaford, Phoebe A. (Phoebe Ann), 1829-1921; Wilbour, Charlotte B. (Charlotte Beebe), 1833-1914; General Federation of Women's Clubs--History--Sources; MacDowell Colony--History; Sorosis--New York (N.Y.)--History--Sources; Literature--Societies, etc.--New York (State)--New York; Temperance--United States--Societies, etc.; Women--United States--Social conditions; Women--United States--Societies and clubs--History--Sources; Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; New York (N.Y.)--Clubs--History--Sources; New York (N.Y.)--Intellectual life--History--Sources
The following records are also available on microfiche in History of Women located in the William Allen Neilson Library: Minutes, 1868-1937; Executive Committee Minutes, 1884-1907; Report of the 21st Anniversary of Sorosis celebrated by a Convention of Clubs held in New York City, March 1889; Selections from the Writings of the Presidents of Sorosis, A Souvenir of the Breakfast at Sherry's, March 30, 1893.
- I. MEETINGS 1868-1965, 5.25 linear ft.
  This series is divided into two subseries: General meetings and Executive Committee meetings each of which is arranged chronologically. The General Meeting minutes include both Social Days and Business Days. Earlier minutes (1868-1925) are bound. Printed cards listing the questions for discussion at specific meetings are also included.
- II. ADMINISTRATION AND ORGANIZATION 1870-1985, 2 linear ft.
  This series is divided into three subseries: Programs, Committees, and Yearbooks. The Programs subseries contains printed programs for meetings between 1883 and 1913. The Committees subseries consists of material related to the twenty-one committees that have been active in Sorosis at various times between 1879 and 1967. The committee records are arranged alphabetically. The Yearbooks subseries contains yearbooks printed by Sorosis that consist of lists of the members and officers, and by-laws. Some of the yearbooks contain schedules of events for the upcoming Sorosis year. There is a broken run of these yearbooks, 1889-1914; 1935-1983.
- III. HISTORY 1871-1973, undated, .75 linear ft.
  This series has two subseries: Anniversaries and Writings and publications. The first subseries includes reports of anniversary celebrations (1872-90) and anniversary programs (1871-1979). The twenty-fifth, seventieth, seventy-fifth, and hundredth have their own sections and are arranged chronologically. There are also photographs from the hundredth anniversary located in Oversized box 30. The Writings and publications subseries contains books and essays on the history of Sorosis written by its members as well as press clippings pertaining to Sorosis history. Of particular interest is a history by Jennie June Croly, Sorosis: Its Origins and History (1886).
- IV. OFFICERS 1894-1950, .75 linear ft.
  There are two subseries in this series: Presidents and Other officers. The Presidents subseries contains information on two early presidents of Sorosis: Charlotte Beebe Wilbour and Jane Cunningham Croly. The former consists of speeches by Wilbour and an address by Deborah Jackson McLeod about Wilbour (1973), and the latter consists of a biography of Croly written by her daughter, and Memories of Jane Cunningham Croly "Jennie June" compiled by members of Sorosis after her death. In addition there are selected annual reports by the President which provide a record of Sorosis activies as well as lists of the presidents (1897-1901). Other officers contains reports of additional officers including the Recording Secretary, the Vice President, the Corresponding Secretary, and the Chairman of Reception. It also contains "Chairman of Executive's Work" by E.F. Turtle, a description of the work taken on by the Chairman of the Executive in 1929.
- V. MEMBERS 1868-1975, undated, .75 linear ft.
  This series contains three subseries: Lists, Writings and Membership Corporation Law. Included in the Lists subseries are the earliest membership list (1870-71), membership and attendance lists (1868-1968), typed "Who's Who" (1947-8 and circa 1980), a binder of biographical information about deceased members (circa 1975) and death notices (1967-71). The "Who's Who" contains education, birth and death dates, and profession as well as information about the member's activities within Sorosis. The Writings subseries contains writings by Sorosis members. These include unpublished manuscripts (1893-1966), miscellaneous publications (1932-1964), and three books written by Gladys Ewing Combes. The Membership Corporation Law is an old statute of the State of New York that was combined into the current Non-For-Profit Corporation Law and dictates how an organization may be formed. The Sorosis copy of the Membership Corporation Law is fragmentary, containing only sections 6, 11, 14 and 15 and is undated.
- VI. PUBLICATIONS 1869-1966, .5 linear ft.
  This series consists of publications produced by and about Sorosis and includes clippings and articles (1886-1901); The Women's Cycle (1890); Sorosis Monthly Bulletins (1955-78); Esther Herrmann Testimonial (1902); Sorosis Verse (1938); and Sorosis: A Federated Woman's Club (1982).There are additional publications in SERIES V. MEMBERS.
- VII. RELATED ORGANIZATIONS 1885-1937, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains information and materials pertaining to the Women's Congress, the MacDowell Colony, the New York State Federation of Women's Clubs, the Ossoli Circle, the Soldiers and Sailors Club and the General Federation of Women's Clubs. These organizations were affiliated with, or related to, Sorosis.
- VIII. MEMORABILIA 1880-1968, 2.25 linear ft.
  This series contains books created by Sorosis, including numerous scrapbooks and the Sorosis Valentine Party Book. There are also books and other items given to Sorosis, such as Four Centuries After: Or, How I Discovered Europe by Ben Holt, two gavels, sheet music, a guestbook, awards, items commemorating Sorosis-related events and three portraits of Charlotte Beebe Wilbour, one painted and two in plaster.
- SERIES I. MEETINGS
  - Social and business
    - Minutes
      - 1868-80 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - 1880-95 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      - 1895-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
      - 1912-22 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
      - 1921-25 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 1925-Mar 1937 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
      - Apr 1937- Mar 1943 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
      - Feb 1943-65 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
      - 1968, 1974-76 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Questions for Discussion 1884-92, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, [see also SERIES II. ADMINISTRATION AND ORGANIZATION-Committees-Executive]
    - Minutes
      - 1883-1907 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
      - 1907-37 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
      - Apr 1937-65 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
      - 1965-79 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
- SERIES II. ADMINISTRATION AND ORGANIZATION
  - Programs
    - 1883-94 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 1895-1913 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Articles of Incorporation, Constitution, and by-laws 1874 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Committees
    - Art 1947-48 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Civics 1942-48 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Current Events 1896-1967 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Drama 1886-1948 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Education 1895-1961 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Executive
      - Annual reports and correspondence 1927-50 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Procedure and Duties 1970-73 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - History 1968 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - House and Home 1886-1903 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - International Relations 1943-45 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Knitting (WWII) 1944-45 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Legislative 1944-49 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Literature 1945-50 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Membership 1944-48 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Motion Pictures 1944-47 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Music 1894-1950 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Nominating 1894-1922 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Poetry 1943-49 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Reception 1945-47 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Resolutions 1879-97 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Science (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Special and Non-permanent (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - World's Columbian Exhibition 1892-[18?]93 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Special occasions 1874-98, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks
    - 1868-85 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1889-1914 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1935-83 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
- SERIES III. HISTORY, [see also SERIES II. ADMINISTRATION AND ORGANIZATION-Committees-History]
  - Anniversaries
    - Reports 1872-90 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Programs
      - 1871-1929 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - 1930-72 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - 1955-79 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
      - Twenty-fifth 1893 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Seventieth 1938 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Seventy-Fifth 1943 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Ninety-ninth 1967, [see also SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA] (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Hundredth, [see also Oversize box 30] (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - A Century of Sorosis, 1868-1968 by Marguerite Dawson Winant, 1968 (2 copies) (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence 1968 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Writings and publications
      - Croly, Jennie June, Sorosis: Its Origins and History, 1886 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Fairfield, Frances Gerry, The Clubs of New York: with an account of the origin, progress, present condition and membership of the leading clubs; an essay on New York club-life [includes Croly, Sorosis Its Origins and History] 1873
      - Ross, Isabel, "Historical Ladies on Parade" undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Allen, Elizabeth Akers, "Backward, turn backward, oh Time in Your Flight" 1890 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Speeches, plays, and press clippings regarding Sorosis history 1954-66, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. OFFICERS
  - President, [see also SERIES V. MEMBERS - Publications by Sorosis Members]
    - Charlotte Beebe Wilbour
      - Speeches
        - "Soul to Soul" 1856-58 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - "The Inviolable Home" 1873 (Box 16, Folder 10)
        - "Address at the Third Anniversary of Egyptian Women" 1887 (Box 16, Folder 11)
        - "Why We Ask the Ballot" 1871 (Box 16, Folder 12)
        - "Honor Among Women" 1871 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - Address by Deborah Jackson McLeod about C. Beebe Wilbour 1973 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Jane Cunningham Croly
      - President of Sorosis - Mrs. Croly, biography by her daughter (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Memories of Jane Cunningham Croly "Jennie June", 1904 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - President's Annual Reports 1930-48 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Presidents of Sorosis 1897-1901 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Officers
    - Officer's Annual Reports 1894-1950 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Turtle, E.F., "Chairman of Executive's Work" 1929, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
- SERIES V. MEMBERS
  - Lists
    - Roll of Members 1874, 1891-1963 (Box 17, Folder 7-8)
    - Membership 1870-71 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Attendance and membership (bound) 1868-1968 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "Who's Who" in Sorosis 1947-8, circa 1980 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - Deceased members of Sorosiscirca 1975 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Death notices 1967-71 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Writings
    - Unpublished manuscript 1893-1966, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous publications 1932-64 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
    - Combes, Gladys Ewing (Box 19)
      - Homespun 1946 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - It Is Christmas 1958 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - A Poetry Pilgrimage Through Europe 1951 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Membership Corporation Lawundated (Box 19, Folder 6)
- SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
  - Clippings and articles 1886-1901 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - The Woman's Cycle 1890 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Monthly Bulletins 1955-68 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Monthly Bulletins 1969-78 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Esther Herrmann Testimonial 1902 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Sorosis Verse 1938 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Sorosis: A Federated Woman's Club 1982 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- SERIES VII. RELATED ORGANIZATIONS
  - Women's Congress (A.A.W.) Programs 1873, 1887 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - MacDowell Colony, Sorosis studio: photograph undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - New York State Federation of Women's Clubs 1894-1951, [see also SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA] (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Ossoli Circle: A Chronological History, 1885-1960 by Sadie Boyd Saxton and Elizabeth Skaggs Bowman, circa 1960 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Soldiers and Sailors Club, New York City: correspondence 1924-37 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs 1920-24, [see also SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA] (Box 20, Folder 10)
- SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA
  - Awards 1890-1966 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Guestbookcirca 1880s (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous material for scrapbooks: correspondence 1876-1920 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Sheet music
    - "Sorosis" by Anne Boul 1982 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - "Little Ioccate" by Elsa A. Stiefel 1964 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - "Happy Birthday" by Elsa A. Stiefel 1964 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - "Don't Be Sorrowful Darling" by Alice Croly and A.J. Abbey undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Sorosis Valentine Party Book 1869 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Four Centuries After: Or, How I Discovered Europe by Ben Holt, 1893 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 99th Anniversary: photographs 1967 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Women's Clubs Commemorative Postage Stamp Binder 1966 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - New York State Federation of Women's Clubs 119th Anniversary Scroll 1987 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Portraits of C.W. Wilbour (Box 23)
  - Gavels (2) (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1896-1904 (Box 24)
    - Sorosis Inter-American Committee 1916-25 (Box 24)
    - 1905-29 (Box 25)
    - 1930-47 (Box 26)
    - 1947-60 (Box 27)
    - 1960-71 (Box 28)
    - circa 1959-77 (Box 29)
    - 1970-73 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified 1905-30 (Box 30)